So now that we know which tools we use and why testing in general is a good idea,
imdi, hangi aralar kullandmz ve genel olarak test etmenin neden iyi bir
we of course have to find out what we should test and there, the answer is straightforward.
fikir olduunu biliyoruz, tabii ki neyi test etmemiz gerektiini ve orada neyin doru olduunu bulmak zorundayz.
Actually writing good tests is quite complex and requires a lot of practice which is also one of the
Aslnda iyi testler yazmak olduka karmaktr ve ok fazla pratik gerektirmektedir ki bu da bunun
reasons why this is no complete testing guide,
tam bir test klavuzunun olmamasnn nedenlerinden
not at all.
biri de deildir.
So in general, here are some things you would not want to test,
Genel olarak, burada test etmek istemeyeceiniz baz eyler
you don't want to test the library,
var, ktphaneyi test etmek
you don't want to test react or axios or redux itself,
istemiyorsunuz, tepkiyi veya aksiyomu test etmek istemiyorsunuz ya da kendini
these are third party libraries which already were tested by the developers.
yenilemek istemiyorsunuz, bunlar zaten test edilmi olan nc parti ktphaneleridir. gelitiricileri.
You don't need to test if they work correctly,
Doru bir ekilde alp almadklarn test
you don't need to test if the store, the redux store is working correctly,
etmenize gerek yoktur, maaza, redux maazasnn dzgn alp almadn test etmenize
you want to test the code
gerek yoktur, uygulamanza
you add to your application and there you want to test the code which does not use that library.
eklediiniz kodu test etmek istersiniz ve burada kodu test etmek istediiniz bu ktphaneyi kullanmaz.
So for example, if you're sending an axios post request, you don't need to test if that is sent successfully,
rnein, bir akson gnderi istei gnderiyorsanz, bunun baaryla gnderilip gnderilmediini snamanza gerek yoktur. Baarsz olursa muhtemelen
if it fails you probably have no internet connection, it's not the axios library. You typically want
nternet balantnz olmaz, bu da Axios ktphanesi deildir. Tipik olarak byle bir kullanm durumunda sunucumdan
to fake data you get back from my server in such a use case and just test what you are doing with such returned
geri dndnz sahte verileri almak istiyorsunuz ve sadece bu tr geri dndrlen verilerle yaptnz eyi
data
test
so that's the idea behind testing.
edin, bylece testin arkasndaki fikir budur.
Additionally you don't want to test too complex connections especially in react,
Ek olarak, zellikle tepki olarak ok karmak balantlar test etmek istemezseniz, bir
there is the danger of testing that you click a button in one component and you change something in
bileendeki bir dmeyi tkladnzdan ve tamamen farkl bir bileendeki bir eyi deitirdiinizden
a totally different component.
dolay test etme tehlikesi vardr.
Now you don't have to test if react is able to use the concept of props to emit an event and pass that
imdi, tepkinin bir olay yaynlamak ve bunu iletmek iin sahne konseptini kullanp kullanamayacan
on,
test
you would be interested in testing if the button click in your react triggers a specific prop in the
etmek zorunda deilsiniz, tepkinizdeki dmenin tklatlmas ilk etapta belirli bir pervane
first place
tetikliyorsa veya
or if the change in data you receive via props in one component leads to a different result being rendered,
Bir bileende sahne zerinden aldnz verilerdeki deiiklik, farkl bir sonuca yol aar, yani
that is what you want to test.
test etmek istediiniz eydir.
There are some testing guides which goes so far to say for react components, you only need to test if
Reaksiyon bileenleri iin imdiye kadar sylenen baz test klavuzlar vardr, sadece bir tepkime bileeninin
a react component itself is rendered correctly.
doru ekilde ilendiini test etmeniz gerekir.
Now I will show you how to test different thing with react components but definitely keep in mind, don't
imdi size farkl eyleri tepki bileenleri ile nasl test edeceinizi gstereceim ama kesinlikle aklnzda
test too complex connections.
bulundurun, ok karmak balantlar test etmeyin.
So these are the things you don't want to test,
Yani bunlar test etmek istemediiniz
what are you going to test then? Typical examples are isolated units,
eyler, ne zaman test edeceksiniz? Tipik rnekler yaltlm birimlerdir, oluturduunuz
you want to test that reducer function you created,
redktr fonksiyonunu test etmek istersiniz, yarattnz
you want to test that component function you created,
bu bileen fonksiyonunu test etmek istersiniz, ayrca
you also want to test conditional output
eer bileeniniz eer bu zellik doruysa, ilenen
if your component has a property which leads to something being rendered if that property is true, then
bir eye neden olan bir zellii varsa, koullu kty test etmek istersiniz Daha sonra bunun
you want to test if this really happens.
gerekten olup olmadn test etmek istersiniz.
What happens if some property changes in your component?
Bileeninizde baz zellikler deiirse ne olur?
Does that affect the output correctly?
Bu k doru olarak etkiler mi?
These are things you want to test in your unit tests.
Bunlar nite testlerinde test etmek istediiniz eyler.
Now with that knowledge gained, let's learn how we actually write unit tests in a react app.
imdi kazandmz bu bilgi sayesinde, bir tepki uygulamasnda gerekte birim testleri yazdmz renelim.